As I was looking at the Bismar, I saw
all these little winking lights and I
thought, "Oh, isn't that pretty?" And
all of a sudden, I realized that what I
thought was pretty was death in
destruction in the form of about 8 tons
of metal coming my way.
The weather had deteriorated
considerably and we flew off um into
cloud in snow and appalling really
flying conditions.
>> 12,000 y is 6 nautical miles. 6 nautical
miles to class was black.
[music]
At the end of May 1941, [music] some of
the world's most powerful warships
jeweled in the middle of the Atlantic.
It was to be one of the last great
battles of the era of naval gunnery. It
was a series of brutal encounters all
revolving around the flagship of the
Germans marine Bismar.
[music]
Bismar is is a quantum leap for the
Germans and no no question. Bismar is as
capable as anything that the British
have got.
>> Bismar is a very impressive warship. She
is extremely dangerous.
[music] Bismar was now loose in the
Atlantic. The Admiral were now trying to
find whatever ships they could and throw
them at the problem.
But the British had one job, to sink
Bismar.
If left unchecked, Bismar threatened to
dominate the Atlantic and starve Britain
of the vital food and military supplies
that flowed from the rest of the world.
The Admiral T had no choice. Bismar had
to be stopped.
On Valentine's Day 1939 at the Bloom and
Voss shipyard in Hamburg, the biggest
ship ever built in Europe was launched.
It was a triumphant day for Hitler.
He had swept to power on the promise of
overturning the Treaty of Versailles and
returning Germany to a position of pride
and power.
And now he was christening one of the
most powerful ships afloat, a stark
statement of intent.
He concluded his speech.
May the German soldiers and officers who
will have the honor to command this ship
one day prove themselves worthy of the
name.
The Bismar
Bismar is quite a large battleship for
her era. She is about 250
m in length, which is fairly impressive,
and 30 m in the beam, so she's wider
than a lot of contemporary battleships.
This helps to make her a very steady gun
platform. She's able to make a very
respectable speed of 29 knots at full
speed, and that is quite fast. What's
important about that is it's a speed
that she can maintain in all weathers.
Um, a lot of ships have a rated maximum
speed, but it often drops in bad
weather. Bismar can push through and
maintain her maximum speed when
conditions are rough. Her armorament is
quite impressive. She has eight 15inch
guns mounted in twin turrets, two
forward, two off. Uh lastly, there's
Bismar's armor and protection scheme. In
keeping with traditional German warship
building practice, they have emphasized
what the more hyperbole would call
unsinkability. She has an incredible
amount of internal subdivision, making
her very hard to flood and therefore to
sink. Her armor protection is comparable
to most modern battleships of the era.
And not only does she have very
impressive protection on the side of the
hull with a a fairly dense armor belt.
Her turrets are very well protected and
her command space has a very heavily
armored conning tower. So between all of
this, Bismar is a very impressive
warship. She's by no means the best
battleship of her generation, but she is
extremely dangerous.
>> Bismar is is a quantum leap for the
Germans. No, no question. Um, so prior
to Bismar coming into service, their
most powerful ships are are what would
nickname the twins, the Shanho and
Nisnau. These are relatively small. The
Germans call them battleships. The
British always call them battle
cruisers. Actually, what they are is a
development of the Panza Shifer. So
they're armed with 11in guns. They're
quite fast. Um but they're they're not
really a match on a one-on-one for any
British battleship afloat at that point.
Um Bismar is Bismar is as capable as
anything that the British have got.
>> Radar had designed the Bismar as a
commerce raider. As such, it was
probably unstoppable. If Bismar had
broken out into the Atlantic, as other
cruisers and uh and smaller ships had
done throughout 1939 and 1940,
the British would have a real problem.
They had lacked the ships with the
firepower to be able to take on Bismar
effectively on the high seas.
>> But it would be 2 years before Bismar
was ready to threaten the seas. two
years it would see Western Europe fall
almost entirely under Nazi control.
The UK had weathered the pounding from
the Luvafa and avoided invasion by the
Vermar. But on the fringes of Europe,
she was still desperately vulnerable.
Britain now relied on fragile cargo
routes that crisscrossed the oceans for
her food and vital supplies that allowed
her to continue resisting Nazi
domination.
Grand Admiral Radar, head of the German
Navy, had witnessed the successes of the
army and Luvafa as they had dominated
central Europe, but also had seen how
they'd struggled to subdue Britain.
He was keen to remain useful in the eyes
of the furer and add naval victories to
Germany's impressive list of
achievements.
It would now be the turn of the
cremarine to try and break the British.
So the German Navy in the Second World
War, the most important thing to realize
about it is it's terribly small. Um,
nevertheless, they've used it
operationally. Um, most notably perhaps
in in Norway in 1940 when they use
almost their entire fleet to transport
an army and carry out a surprise attack
on Norway. They have their pocket
battleships, the famous Panza Shifer.
They they go out on commerce raiding
missions. They're in place at the
beginning of the war. So by 1941, you've
got a German Navy that has been
probably, to be fair, doing the best it
can given the resources it has.
>> The German Navy had been designed on
different lines from the Royal Navy. The
Royal Navy was all about sea power and
sea control. Controlling the sea lanes
and imposing its will on the enemy.
Essentially the same thing it had done
in the Napoleonic Wars and during the
First World War. The Germans were in the
business of sea denial, limiting the the
enemy's fleet and pinning it in place,
but also then attacking his sea lanes.
When we think about the commerce raiding
of the Germans in the Second World War,
we tend to focus on Ubot and submarines.
Um, and clearly that's what does the
most damage overall during the war.
However, if you are able to put big
capital ships to sea as well as
submarines, that's the dream ticket in
terms of commerce raiding because if you
want to protect your merchant ships from
submarines, what do you do? You group
them into a convoy with lots of small
warships that are anti-ubmarine ships
around it. Job done. However, if a
battleship like Bismar rocks up, then
the battleship can destroy all those
small escorts and the convoy. So, the
only thing that a convoy can do if a
battleship like Bismar appears is
scatter. And if it scatters, then all
those individual merchant ships can be
sunk by submarines. pot was a gamecher
for it. Um came in the spring of 1940
with the capture of French ports on the
Atlantic particularly breast which had a
um they had dry docks, they had port
facilities which could serve as both a
yubot fleet but also if German
battleships and heavy cruisers broke out
into the Atlantic, [music] they could
use places like Breast as a base.
>> [music]
>> Raider was quick to take advantage of
the newly captured French ports on the
Atlantic coast. He based his Yubot wolf
packs there and sent them out deep into
the Atlantic to prey upon British supply
lines. The impact was immediate and
devastating. The Hubot captains called
this the happy time.
Despite these successes, most still
believed that only warships on the
surface could deal a decisive blow in
the campaign. And so, as Bismar
underwent its final sea trials, Radar
launched Operation Berlin in January
1941, two fast, powerful battleships,
Nisnau and Shanho, swept through the
Atlantic from Greenland to the Azors,
smashing into Britain's vulnerable
shipping lanes. The threat of Germany's
surface fleet was now very real.
Raider was thrilled with the success of
Operation Berlin and desperate to try
and repeat it. This time with his new
super weapon, Bismar.
Unfortunately for him, there were no
other big gunned battleships that were
operational. But Bismar would sail
anyway, accompanied only by a squadron
of smaller vessels and the heavy cruiser
Prince Oegan.
The men in command of Bismar were Vice
Admiral Ga Luchens and his captain Ernst
Linderman. Lutens had been in charge of
operation Berlin and was now about to
lead Germany's most potent naval asset
out on another commerce raiding mission,
Operation Rhuong.
And so on the 19th of May 1941, the
world's heaviest commissioned battleship
slid out of a dockyard on the German
occupied Baltic coast, escorted by her
consort, Prince Oegan. On board the
Prince Oegan was a small team from the
propaganda company tasked with reporting
on the mission. Amazingly with them was
a cameraman called Lagaman. Bismar's
[music] maiden operation was filmed.
Bismar wanted to avoid contact with the
Royal Navy as much as possible. The plan
was to get out into the open Atlantic
and start raiding, not to engage other
capital ships.
But to get there completely unseen would
prove impossible. Within hours of
leaving port, a Swedish cruiser spotted
the flotilla sailing west through the
Baltic Sea. The Swedish reporter of its
not named the ship, and contact was lost
once it left Swedish waters. The message
that made its way to the British Admiral
only read.
As Bismar and Prince Oegan slipped out
into the North Sea and up towards
Norway, the British were already flying
reconnaissance sorties over the
Scandinavian coast.
On the 21st of May, flying officer
Michael Sutling flew over a fjord near
Bergen and took a photograph that sent a
chill to the core of the British Admiral
team. The size of the ship in the
photograph could only mean one thing.
Admiral John Tovi put the Royal Navy on
high alert.
Bismar was loose.
So to understand the Royal Navy in 1941,
we we actually need to rewind quite a
bit actually. Um actually let's rewind
to 1815 very very briefly because at the
end of the Napoleonic Wars that the
Royal Navy is the single most powerful
dominant force in the world. Um there's
nothing else to touch it and that's the
case for the whole of the 19th century.
So the Royal Navy goes into the First
World War with a a new young threat at
sea and also no operational experience
fighting sea battles for the best part
of hundred years because there hasn't
been anyone to take them on. Lots and
lots of lessons are learned for the
Royal Navy during the First World War um
about command and control. Um and the
the guys who were the the junior
officers commanding ships or first left
tenants of ships in the First World War,
those are the people who are running the
Navy in the Second World War. So they've
got the men and they've also got the
ships. Um the the Royal Navy at the
start of the Second World War, it has
its gaps, but it's still the most
powerful, the most potent navy in the
world. So you've got um a mix of older
ships that are being refurbished and
that's actually a program that is um is
underway when the war breaks out.
>> The battleships particularly were old.
However, five new ones were building in
1941 and two of them by May had entered
service with the home fleet, the King
George V and the Prince of Wales. So
that at least gave the British modern
speedy battleships.
>> That said, they've got considerable
things facing them. Although the Royal
Navy is huge, it is very, very
stretched. They have gone into the
Second World War confident that they
could fight the Germans. That's fine.
um they could fight the Germans and the
Italians with the French alongside them,
but they lose the French in 1940. So
suddenly they're up against the German
Navy combined with the Italian Navy and
they're doing it on their own.
[music]
I'm deep beneath the streets of
Liverpool now in Derby House. And this
is one of the most important spaces of
the British war effort because it was
from here that the British directed
operations in the Battle of the
Atlantic. Here is where the information
was gathered and plotted so that it
could be instantly accessible. You've
got all the states readiness of aircraft
squadrons, of convoys, of naval assets,
and then those assets will be plotted on
this amazing map of the North Atlantic.
You've got military vessels and
submarines, enemy and allied. You've
also got merchant marine convoys, ONS,
that means outbound from Britain. HX
means it's left Halifax heading for the
UK. It gives commanders here a realtime
view of what is going on in this battle
space. It is essential to British
success in the allimportant battle of
the Atlantic. And as such, it was at the
heart of that titanic month, May 1941,
when the British attempted to catch the
Bismar. It was quite the undertaking.
The British home fleet left their base
in Scotland. These convoys were stripped
of their military escorts. All
non-essential missions were cancelled.
It was the biggest single naval
operation of the Second World War thus
far. And at its heart was the pride of
the fleet, the mighty Hood.
Was a massive ship and she was beautiful
to look at. She was wonderful looking
ship. You know, she was long and uh
perfectly symmetrical. Two turrets
forward, two mass, two funnels, two
turrets after. marvelous looking ship.
>> I'd never seen anything quite so
powerful and beautiful. First of all,
beautiful for a battleship sounds an
awful word, but it's there was no other
word to describe her.
[music]
Hood was pretty much equivalent in size
to Bismar. She was about 860 ft in
length, which was a very large vessel
indeed, somewhat slimmer than Bismar at
only 100 foot in the beam. Uh she was
therefore perhaps best to describe her
as an ocean greyhound. She was designed
to be fast and she was designed to be
very powerful. There's also a similarity
in primary armorament. She has eight
15-in guns dispersed in very much the
same way we see on the Bismar. Two twin
turrets forward, two twin turrets aft.
Hood was quite respectably protected,
but her protection scheme was dated. So
although her armor was only marginally
thinner than Bismar's in terms of
horizontal protection and was actually
thicker in places around her turrets,
Hood had been designed before the
effects of long range plunging fire had
been fully understood. And because she
had never had the comprehensive refit
that had graced a couple of the Royal
Navy's other capital ships, it meant
that she went into battle with a scheme
of protection that was inadequate to the
demands of modern naval warfare. The
final element, of course, was her speed.
That long thin hull was meant to
purchase a very high speed. And in fact,
the reason her upper deck is so low at
the stern uh was basically to save
weight, to squeeze as many knots as they
could out of this design, which had
already sacrificed a lot of weight in
other directions. As completed, Hood
could manage 31 to 32 knots fairly
easily. A very high speed for a ship
this size. But unfortunately, by 1941,
her engines, although maintained, were
aging. And unlike Bismar, she wasn't
designed in the same way to cope with
very heavy weather.
So while her printed speed as complete
might have been 31 knots, her actual
speed in 1941 was probably no better
than Bismar's. It may even have been a
knot or so slower. By the start of the
Second World War, Hood was probably the
most famous warship in the world. During
the inter war years, Hood spent most of
her time showing the flag. She toured
the world and was a floating embodiment
of British sea power. She looked
powerful. She looked sleek. She looked
above all, she looked elegant. She's the
perfect vessel for showing the flag,
brass bands playing, cocktail parties,
and she'll impress anyone. The trouble
was during that time she hadn't been
overhauled. She could have been modified
and improved and rearmored, but she was
too useful as a as the poster child of
British sea power.
>> There is a a mythical status to her that
is hard to defend. Um, she is a battle
cruiser. This is an evolutionary dead
end for warships really that that really
should have been killed off after the
battle of Jutland when three of them
blow up and sink. Their best dispense is
supposed to be their speed. So they are
they look like a battleship. Um, they
have the same guns as a battleship. They
do not have the armor protection of a
battleship and as a consequence they can
go faster and they're supposed to be
used for scouring the oceans of commerce
raiders. So you want a battle cruiser to
go and find a pocket battleship and sink
it. You do not want them standing up in
the line against battleships and they
learn this at Jutland. Um so they don't
build anymore and actually the Royal
Navy only enters the Second World War
with three of them um heard renown and
repulse all of which date back to the
the closing years of the First World
War. They are laid down and completed
during the first world war. Renown and
repulse actually see service in the
first world war and Hood comes in
shortly afterwards. Um so she is built
really with problems. She gets this
nickname the mighty Hood and she is
fundamentally the wrong ship to attach
that label to. They really should not
have done that.
Despite those concerns, Hood, under the
command of Vice Admiral Lancelot
Holland, would be at the head of the
strike force against Bismar, and should
be accompanied by a brand new
battleship, HMS Prince of Wales.
The pair were ordered to cruise to the
south of Iceland, where she could use
her speed to intercept Bismar, whichever
route she took to get into the Atlantic.
Admiral Toby knew that there were three
options available to Lutons, but still
didn't know which he would take. He
therefore ordered heavy cruisers to take
up positions between Shetland and the
Pharaohs in the Icelandic Pharaoh Gap
and in the Denmark Straits, the channel
of water between Iceland and Greenland.
The Royal Navy had set its trap.
Whichever way into the rich hunting
grounds of the Atlantic that Bismar and
Prince Oegan chose to take, the Navy
would be waiting. Whether it was between
the Pharaohs and Iceland or the Denmark
Strait, between Iceland and Greenland,
the German ships would have to pass
through a British net. All these British
ships had to do now was keep their eyes
open and wait.
On the 22nd of May, Bismar and Prince
Oegan were cruising off the coast of
Norway and Lutons needed to decide which
passage they would take. He knew that
the Royal Navy would be out there
somewhere, but he didn't know where. At
1200 hours, he ordered a new course.
Bismar and Prince Oegan would try and
break out into the Atlantic through the
Denmark Straits.
Stationed in the straits were sister
ships HMS Norfolk and Suffukk. They'd
been dispatched there on the 21st of May
and their crews had been waiting
patiently in foul North Atlantic
weather. They would be the trip wire for
the entire British plan.
Suddenly at 20 7
to my right shouted ship and then two
ships. I swam up this way, steamed up
fast from behind us. Come up behind us
water.
What had actually happened is that the
the closed right down somebody lift it
and they were there quarter and I know
that I know the distance because right
behind me in the fall control it was a
communication person who was repeating
uh messages from the radar office. And
although we'd seen them first
officially, I heard him say echo bearing
green 140
12,000
that was 12,000 y 12,000 y is 6 nautical
miles
6 nautical miles for a ship to us.
As the German ships are pushing through,
they are spotted by the British cruiser
HMS Suffukk on patrol in the Denmark
Strait. Now Suffukk and Norfolk, they're
not powerful enough to engage Bismar
clearly, but what they can do is
absolutely classic cruiser work, which
is to find the enemy, report the enemy's
presence, and then shadow them. And
that's what they do. They they pick up
the Germans. The British have the
advantage of radar, so they start to
shadow the Germans through the Denmark
Strait. The Germans try and throw them
off. They know that the risks are there.
Um, periodically, Bismar turns and fires
at them. It's very it's a dance that the
British are very used to. They pull out
of range, they pull back in again and
keep methodically following them while
heavier forces can be summoned up. Um
and the nearest force that can be
brought up um is HMS Hood together with
the brand new battleship HMS Prince of
Wales.
[music]
The British were planning to steal a
march on the Germans. So they in fact uh
went to action stations very shortly
after midnight on the morning of the
24th of May. The Germans were at a
slightly lower alert level. They they
knew there were British cruisers tailing
them, but those cruisers didn't
represent an existential threat. They
were more of a highly dangerous
nuisance. Um so the Germans were at the
next alert level down. What that meant
was that some of their crews were able
to rest while about twothirds of the
crew were closed up. And when they did
sight Hood and Prince of Wales, it was a
simple matter to go to full action
stations and summon the remaining crew
to their battle stations. So the state
of play when these two forces meet is
quite interesting because at the
beginning, at the outset, you would
think the British have the advantage
actually. Hood, we've discussed, is
quite old. Um, but she's still got those
powerful 15-in guns. Um, she's got her
speed. Um, and she's accompanied by
Prince of Wales, which is another
battleship, brand new, 14inch gunned,
quadruple turrets, you know, a very
powerful unit. Um, set against that, the
Germans have Bismar. Now, Bismar is also
unwe and untried. We tend to forget
that. Bismar and Prince of Wales are
both on their first operational
deployments. Prince of Wales has been
rushed into hers. Bismar's had a little
bit more workup time, but neither of
them have fought a battle. Um, and then
the Germans have Prince Oegan, also
brand new, heavy cruiser. Realistically,
she's pretty outmatched. Um, Prince is
not designed to go toe-to-toe with
either Hood or Prince of Wales. The
British also have two cruisers.
So, there's a stronger British force
there.
[music]
Prince of Wales uh Hood's consort in
this operation is a brand new
battleship. She's one of the new King
George Vclass battleships. These are
very powerful warships. They're very
welld designigned. They're reasonably
fast and her presence there should have
been enough to ensure a British victory.
But there was a lot going on under the
surface. The first was Prince of Wales
was extremely new. Her crew had only
just been assigned. Many of them were
inexperienced and the ship still had
civilian contractors aboard because
she'd been rushed into service so
quickly and sent out to accompany uh
Hood. So what this meant in practice was
you have a ship with a crew who are
unfamiliar with her. Um, the ship has
not undergone what they would call a
shakeddown cruise in order to knock her
systems into order, um, iron out all the
kinks, identify potential mechanical
problems and rectify them, none of
that's really had a chance to happen. So
although on paper, Prince of Wales is an
extremely powerful asset, she is not all
that she seems and in many respects is
actually less than she seems.
When dawn came and the two sides spotted
each other, Hood realized that the
Germans weren't quite where he expected
them to be. Shortly before, Luchans had
altered course. Essentially, he's
heading south. Now, he's heading more in
a southeasterly [music] course.
Holland had a decision to make. He could
either continue to shadow the German
ships and wait for Royal Navy
reinforcements to arrive, or he could
engage the enemy. At 5:37 a.m., he made
his decision.
He would fight.
The message was conveyed back to the
Admiral.
Admiral Holland has no other choice
other than to engage Bismar. That's his
job. So the the German job is to avoid
action and to to get through into the
Atlantic. That's Luchin's job. Holland's
job is to stop him. So Holland has to
fight a battle. And actually he's got
trained, experienced crews. I think we
tend to think of the problems with Hood.
The advantage of Hood is she's she's a
long-standing, you know, she's been in
service for a long time. That's an
experienced crew. You know, all any
faults, mechanical faults with Hood have
been ironed out long before. You know,
very coherent unit that knows what it's
doing. And then Prince Wales, a very
powerful new force. So, there's nothing
wrong with Holland's decision. He has to
engage.
The men on board the two British capital
ships were now preparing for battle.
We were all right on the hood because I
mean it was the best. It was the finest
ship in the world and we were safe. No
bother.
There was a certain amount of tension.
Yes. Uh I wouldn't say we thought it was
going to be historic, but we thought
the hood was the best and we would beat
the enemy. But as I've said previously,
there were going to be casualties. You
don't go into any action like that
without expecting casualties. Once
again, it's going to happen to someone
else. It's not going to happen to me.
And over the
loudspeaker system
came a voice we didn't know particularly
and he said,
"This is the chaplain speaking.
This was the prayer between before Edge
Hill.
Oh Lord, thou knowest how busy we shall
be today.
If we forget thee,
do not thou forget us.
Hood was in a lot of danger at the
outset of the engagement. It's very
obvious from the start that the British
are at a disadvantage. They've
approached out of position. Uh the
Germans are very fine off Hood's bow,
which means that they are crossing the
British tea. Their full broadside can be
brought to bear on the British ships,
whereas the British have a a rather
awkward choice to make. They can either
turn to match the Germans, in which case
you have an engagement where Hood is at
a serious disadvantage in terms of her
protection, or they can attempt to close
the range. However, in closing, only the
forward turrets on the Hood and on the
Prince of Wales are able to bear.
>> Holland takes this decision, God knows I
wouldn't want to take it, to to push
close in as as fast as possible before
going into line. So he accepts the fact
that he's going to be outgunned for a
while. Um that the Germans will be able
to bring all their guns to bear on just
his forward guns as they close. So
that's the decision he takes. The reason
why Holland decides to close is to try
and avoid the possibility of plunging
fire as quickly as he can. Now what is
plunging fire? That is where you elevate
your guns bit like a military howitzer
and you fire a shell that goes up in the
air and then plunges down. And what that
does is if you hit the target, you're
going to go through the deck armor
rather than the armor belt around the
side of the ship. Now, on any warship
that the deck armor is more vulnerable
than the armor belt. Um, on Hood, it's a
particular problem because um, Hood is a
battle cruiser. They have sacrificed
armor protection for speed and Hood's
deck armor is really, really not up to
speed. Now, Holland knows this. Um, so
what he wants to do is get under under
the plunge as soon as he can. Blow to
blow like boxers pummeling each other on
the belt armor. Fundamentally he's got
two very powerful ships and the Germans
only have one very powerful ship. He's
pretty confident he can win that.
When the radar had first got this range,
it was somewhere in the region of about
nearly 20,000 yards, I should imagine.
and watching this pointer. It was going
20,000, 19,000,
18,000,
17,000, 16,000. If it would have been me
being a coward, I should have laid off
and eight of the range of the 15-in guns
and probably waloped him from there. And
I thought, my goodness, in a minute we
will be getting out our cutlesses and
going aboard that German and giving them
a good old taste of the Nelsons and the
Drakes.
Hood's huge guns opened fire at 0553,
hurling enormous projectiles, an
astonishing 24 km.
But Hood's crew had made a terrible
mistake. They were firing on the leading
German ship, believing it to be Bismar.
But during the night, Bismar and Prince
Oegan had changed position. So for
several crucial minutes, Hood was firing
at the wrong target.
>> In its own in isolation, it isn't that
important. But the problem is all these
little things are these leveling factors
that then start to give the Germans an
advantage. So you've got some time lost
when they're targeting the wrong ship.
essentially. Not only does that mean
you're losing opportunities to hit
Bismar, but it's also giving Bismar a
free shoot because they're not being
distracted by by gunfire going off
around them and shell splashes in the
water. Um, when you add that to um the
the need [clears throat] to close the
range because of Hood's feeble deck
armor, the mechanical problems on board
Prince of Wales, all these factors then
are starting to to level things up for
the Germans and take away what should
have been a British advantage.
The crew on board the Prince of Wales
made no such error, and despite her
mechanical problems, it was the new
battleship that scored the first hit.
A shell smashed through Bismar's bow
without exploding, but severing fuel
lines. Bismar, like a prize fighter,
absorbed the blows. Then, Captain Ernst
Linderman barked a command to his
gunnery officer Schneider. permission to
fire.
At 0555,
Bismar's guns roared. On board the
Prince Oegan, the camera captured the
huge flares from Bismar's 15-in guns, as
well as the enormous shell splashes
caused by British rounds falling all
around the German ships.
As I was looking at the Bismar, I saw
all these little winking lights and I
thought, "Oh, isn't that pretty?" And
all of a sudden, I realized that what I
thought was pretty was death and
destruction in the form of about 8 tons
of metal coming my way.
Holland had ordered Prince of Wales and
Hood to stay pretty close together to
better coordinate their fire. But this
presented Bismar with an easier target.
Using state-of-the-art Zeiss
stereoscopic rangefinding equipment high
in the superructure of Bismar, the
artillery officer observed where his
shells were landing and edged them ever
closer to the British ship, correcting
his fire. Bismar was closing in. As
Bismar's shells roared overhead, Admiral
Holland realized his terrible mistake.
He calmly ordered, "Shift target to the
right."
His guns would now focus on Bismar, but
he lost valuable minutes.
>> Holland is is is doing the best he can
with the force that he's got available.
And I think he's he's demonstrating a
knowledge of the strengths and
weaknesses of the ships he's got um and
trying to compensate for that in the
best way he can. Um and you know, these
these smaller factors, they they happen
in battle. And I think it's very easy
for us to sit there and and say, well,
the lookouts should have done their job
better and distinguished between Prince
and Bismar. And you know, you can argue
about all these things, but actually
he's got to do the job with the tools he
has. There's always a strong element of
luck. Um, and some of these things just
just go against him. The cards don't
turn in the right way. [music]
Another
salvo from Bismar came screaming in.
This time it was a hit. A shell landed
in an ammunition store. Luckily, there
was not a catastrophic detonation and
fires were contained. Prince Oegan also
scored a hit on Hood. German gunners
smelt blood.
At 6:00 a.m., Admiral Holland made the
decision to turn his ship to bring all
of his guns to bear. At the same time,
Bismar at a distance of about 9 miles
unleashed another savage salvo.
Her monstrous shells dropped all around
Hood until one of them scored another
direct hit.
No one knows where the fatal blow
landed. There's no way that we can know.
But there are two theories that were
advanced at the time and have many
supporters today. One is that the shell
simply plunged through the decks, which
would not be unexpected in terms of what
was understood at the time. A plunging
fire hit that penetrates through this
protection that is not adequate to guard
against it. scores a lucky hit in a
magazine and starts off a chain reaction
which dooms the ship. The other
possibility
is that it might have been what's called
a short where the shell does not
actually hit the ship at first but lands
in the water very close by. And what
happens in the case of a a a hit like
that is that the shell has entered the
water um but by sheer good or bad
fortune depending on whether you're the
recipient um actually travels beneath
the level of the side armor and
penetrates the hull below it. That too
could have caused the chain reaction
that destroyed Hood because of course
the bottom of the ship is where the
magazines are and if a heavy shell like
that gets through and causes a fire then
you have problems.
It's interesting to note that one of the
Hood survivors stated that as Hood was
making her turn and was able to finally
unmask her rear gun batteries,
um X turret, the third one from the bow,
fired. Y turret remained strangely
silent. So it's entirely possible that
whatever was going wrong had begun to go
wrong at that point. Uh regardless,
within the next few minutes, u everyone
saw the explosion which destroyed Hood.
>> Witnesses to that fateful moment say
that a flame like a a blowtorrch flared
up into the sky followed by an almighty
explosion. Hood disintegrated.
I personally didn't hear any explosion
at all. Again, the ship shuddered and we
were all thrown off our feet and all I
saw was a gigantic sheet of flame which
shot round the front of the compass
platform. After after the hit, you you
heard the screams and the uh noise of of
the
carnage that was going on. There was no
order given to abandoned ship. It wasn't
necessary.
On the horizon of the Prince Oegan film,
distant smoke from the stricken Hood can
be seen.
Witnesses likened the devastation to
what happened to HMS Barroom just 6
months after Hood. It too saw its
magazines explode,
ripping the ship apart.
and in the corner of my binoculars where
I could see we were so close I could see
the hood. All of a sudden there was a
huge great orange flash
and then when I looked out from my
binoculars to where the hood was, there
was no hood.
Hood was ripped in half. The third
section sank within seconds. The bowels
rose vertically up into the air. The
guns fired one last eerie salvo. A final
act of defiance from a doomed gun crew.
Within three minutes, the mighty Hood,
the pride of the Royal Navy, the most
famous ship in the world, sank beneath
the waves.
Of 1,418
men on board, only three survived.
We received information that the hood
had been had been sunk.
That sounded impossible.
And we waited for confirmation.
We were very anxious that we should
serve the guns quickly because if the
hood had been sunk, then we had would
have a double job.
As the crew of the Prince of Wales
watched in horror as their comrades were
sucked beneath the waves, the reality of
their own position now suddenly dawned
on them. They were one British ship
facing two Germans. In the next four
minutes, seven shells smashed into
Prince of Wales. The situation was
getting desperate.
We' had a 15-in shell go through the
bridge and explode as it was going out
and killed an awful lot up there.
And a boy of 16 thinks that being
wounded is a nick in the shoulder. But
I in my keenness, I was very very keen
in those days
went to do what I was supposed to do,
start tidying up the bridge. And I went
in and um
expecting to see people and um the first
thing I saw as I went in the wood
paneling was
just little bits of flesh spattered all
around
and that was a very very big shock to
me. I don't think I ever got over that.
[music]
Less than 10 minutes after Hood had
slipped beneath the waves, Captain John
Leech of the Prince of Wales decided
that the odds were stacked too heavily
against him. He ordered a hard turn to
port and for his ship to make an escape
and then to our dismay at about 10 6 the
captain came on and said, I remember his
words hoods blown up, broken into.
Now the hood was alleged by as most
people know
and we were told that Prince had to
withdraw to to repair its damage and
they left suffer on their own.
So it didn't look a very very happy
situation.
The British have been terrified about
what Bismar might have been capable of
if it was unleashed on the Allied supply
routes across the Atlantic. Now, in the
space of just a couple of minutes,
firing just a few salvos, Bismar hadn't
sunk some unarmed merchant ship, but the
pride of the Royal Navy. Britain's worst
fears had been realized.
HMS Norfolk that had been shadowing the
battle sent a simple communicate back to
the Admiral Ty in London.
They released a tur note that same
evening.
During the action, HMS Hood received an
unlucky hit in a magazine and blew up.
There was nothing really in the British
so psyche that could replace a loss so
so dramatic of such a prestigious
warship. It was essentially a huge slap
in the face to British pride and uh
British sense of
naval superiority.
The world had almost turned upside down.
What on earth could the could the Bismar
do next? The Royal Navy itself
is not going to be super surprised by
this. One of the things that has allowed
the Royal Navy to be so dominant for so
many centuries is is culturally they
have always seen ships are assets to be
used and when you use assets you might
lose them. This isn't the first ship the
Royal Navy have lost in action.
Politically um and in terms of domestic
morale it's devastating. The the Hood
has gone and the Hood hasn't just gone.
She's gone in seconds and taken almost
her entire ship's company other than
three men down with her. So that is a a
really significant problem and you have
to look at the wider context without
trying to to divert us too much. This is
not a point where the war is going well
for the British anyway. So from
Churchill downwards this has to be
avenged. It has to be very publicly
avenged.
[music]
In Germany, the news that Hood had been
sunk was met by widespread jubilation.
Gobles made the most of it. It was huge
propaganda coup. Bismar uh had bested
the most famous warship in the world and
the pride of the British fleet. So there
was no stopping uh Germany which could
now break out in the Atlantic and
destroy Allied convoy routes. That was
the message coming out of Germany.
Hitler was delighted. His his support of
radar had been vindicated and for the
moment everything looked rosy.
When word of Bismar's success was
radioed back to Germany, Hitler's
propaganda minister, Joseph Gerbals,
immediately broadcast it to the nation.
Germany now had a huge maritime victory
to cheer alongside its remarkable run of
conquests on the European continent.
The British were devastated.
But that disappointment didn't breed
despondency. Instead, the Admiral Ty
were gripped by an iron determination.
Every ship, every asset was now
redirected to one very simple end
to sink the Bismar.
[music]
>> [music]
>> And then we were hit.
There was a terrific explosion and the
whole ship suddenly dead silence.
>> The sight setter suddenly shouted out,
"The hood's gone."
Someone said, "What?"
And he said, "The hood's gone." And it
was just
unbelievable
that the hood was there one minute and
she was no longer there.
And we were dumbruck with the thought
that the hood had been sunk by the
Bismar.
In May 1941, Germany's newest and most
powerful battleship, Bismar, was
dispatched on her first mission,
Operation Rhuboom.
She would be adding her massive
firepower to the German effort to starve
Britain into submission.
Just 5 days into her maiden voyage,
Bismar was already having a huge impact
on the war in the Atlantic.
She had smashed through the British
blockade, and in an engagement lasting
under 10 minutes, she had sunk the Royal
Navy's toemic flagship, HMS Hood. Bismar
was now in the northern Atlantic and had
British convoys in her sights.
Winston Churchill and many in the
Admiral were plunged into a state of
depression, but the path ahead of them
now lay clear. Hood's loss could not be
in vain. The reputation of the Royal
Navy had to be salvaged at all costs.
Bismar had to be found and destroyed.
Whilst the British reeled from the loss
of the Hood, the crew on Bismar knew
there was another side to the story. She
might have been the most powerful
battleship afloat, but Bismar had not
escaped the battle of the Denmark Strait
unscathed.
>> She had suffered, according to German
records, a total of three hits. Now, two
of these hits are generally agreed to
have been of no real consequence,
cosmetic damage, but nothing worse than
that. But the third hit was the one
which caused serious problems. It struck
somewhere in the region of the bow and
it tore a hole in Bismar's armor. Now,
the hole in itself was not enormous, but
because Bismar was moving at speed, it
exacerbated the flooding and hundreds of
tons of seaater entered the ship before
they were able to try and stabilize the
situation. This caused Bismar's bow to
sink into the water a little and it
reduced her speed by a knot or two. May
not sound significant, but when you're
being pursued, those extra knots can be
critical. The much more serious
consequence of the hit was that it's
severed the connection between Bismar's
forward fuel tanks and her machinery
spaces.
>> This is causing two problems. It's
causing um it's causing problems with
the ship losing weight. She's lost a bit
of speed, but she's also hemorrhaging
fuel oil. Um and that itself causes two
problems. The first is the obvious one.
She hasn't got enough fuel, so that
limits how far she can go. But secondly,
she's leaving an oil trail in the water,
so you can almost It's almost like
breadcrumbs. makes it very easy to
follow and spot, particularly from the
air. So, this is a really significant
problem. And as the Germans are pulling
away, they're they're trying to trying
to do everything they can to to get at
this and patch this. They even try and
send divers down over the side while the
ship's underway. It's really really hard
to do. They they fail. So, this is a
problem that they they never really
resolve. So in the same way that we see
during the action with Hood those little
incremental problems that started to
shift the balance in favor of the
Germans, the Germans are now starting a
process of little incremental issues
that are shifting the odds against them.
>> Admiral Luchin is faced with some
options. He can continue the raid, but
he has less time to do it than he
normally would. Another option is to
return back through the Denmark Strait
and head off to Norway. hook up with a
tanker and try again once the ship's
been patched up a little.
The other option is to head out into the
Atlantic and loop round to breast. The
advantage there is Charhost and Nisnau
were there. Nisnau is damaged. Char is
in refit. But the idea that all three
ships together would then be in the one
port where they could then break out on
mass was was a fairly appealing one to
Luchian.
>> Bismar continues through the Denmark
straight and out into the Atlantic.
There is again some controversy about
whether whether Prince of Wales which is
mechanically unreliable with an
inexperienced ships company and then the
two cruisers should have gone back in
and engaged Bismar and brinsen. Who
knows what the outcome of that would
have been. Either way, what actually
happens is um they opt to shadow again.
The Germans know they need to shake off
this shadowing force as soon as
possible. Whatever their options are,
it's going to be a lot better for them
if nobody knows where they are.
[music]
Linderman wanted to carry out running
repairs and then steer Bismar straight
towards those vital allied shipping
routes across the Atlantic. the original
objective of operation rin
disagreed. Bismar would return to a safe
harbor as quickly as possible.
Churchill knew the danger that Bismar
now posed, so he gambled. He ordered
every available ship in the Royal Navy
into the Atlantic to join the hunt.
The Admiral team were now trying to find
whatever ships they could and throw them
at the problem. Essentially, that meant
one battleship, Toby's flagship, King
George V, a sister ship of the Prince of
Wales, with largely the same gunnery
problems facing her, although not quite
so acute, and also the aircraft carrier
Victorious.
Other ships were around. Uh the
battleship Rodney for instance was
escorting the troop ship Britannic uh
and she was in the Clyde. So the Admiral
team made the decision to peel her away
from that convoy along with most of the
escorting destroyers uh under Captain
Van and add them to Tovy's force. One
remaining force was down in Gibralta.
Vice Admiral Somerville's Force H based
at Gibralta, which could have needed
sail north to intervene.
>> Given the circumstances and and the the
the scale of the catastrophe they have
experienced with the loss of Hood, this
is the appropriate response that there
is a bigger picture here and that bigger
picture is the political picture and
that to be fair is what Winston
Churchill has to think of. He's he's got
half an iron. How is this playing out in
the US? Every time the British get a
knock back in battle, it weakens the
American perception about is is Britain
a country? Is is Britain a viable
investment? Is Britain going to be able
to stay in this war? Um, you know, if if
the Royal Navy loses a capital ship at
sea, that has has consequences that go
way beyond the tactical. Tactically,
she's an old ship and the British have
quite a few more, but politically, it's
it's a real problem. So, it is an
appropriate response.
Despite Bismar's decision to return to
port, her cruiser escort Prince Oen was
still fully operational, able to
continue with Operation Rubong.
At 1812, Bismar looped back to face the
pursuing ships and opened fire, a handy
diversion for the Prince Oegan.
She peeled off and headed south.
Bismar turned back onto her course and
carried on alone.
Despite its condition, Bismar was still
capable of steaming at 28 knots. That's
the same speed that the brand new
flagship of the home fleet, King George
V, was able to do. There was simply no
way Bismar could be caught unless
something changed. The Royal Navy would
have to find a way to slow it down.
The British simply didn't have any
vessels large enough to bring Bismar to
action within range. So at 1600 hours,
Admiral Tovi ordered his aircraft
carrier, HMS Victorious, to prepare her
squadron of torpedo bombers for an
immediate strike.
>> The whole idea of air power at sea was a
fairly new fangled invention. Uh the
British had had achieved great success
in 1940. with their attack on the
Italian fleet at Toronto. But this was a
different different thing entirely. This
was a modern battleship with very good
integrated anti-aircraft defenses
um and being attacked at sea by
essentially raw pilots and raw raw air
crew. So that was a very desperate roll
of the dice.
>> What carrier aviation gives you is the
ability to punch beyond the horizon. And
it basically you need to think of a
carrier aircraft as as a shell that you
can actually file for hundreds of miles.
It's a huge force multiplier. So um the
trick is to get this air strike in and
try and slow Bismar. I mean you'd like
to sinker if you can. It's unlikely but
you're going to give it a go.
The main strike aircraft is the
Swordfish torpedo bomber. Now people
look at the Swordfish and they call it
obsolete because it's a biplane and it
has an open cockpit. I don't know
honestly how many successes the
Swordfish has to score before we stop
calling it obsolete. The Swordfish is an
extremely good naval strike aircraft.
And what we need to understand is is
that actually the requirements for for
naval aircraft are completely different
to the requirements for anything that
you're operating on land. You're not
that worried about speed actually
because you're not going to outrun
anything. You're not going to find
fighter opposition in the middle of the
Atlantic. Um, what you want is something
that can carry a lot of weaponry. It's
very stable, fly in a straight line,
that's what you need in in a good
torpedo bomber, and can absorb a lot of
punishment. And actually, the swordfish
can absorb a phenomenal amount of
punishment. Cannon shells just go
straight through the fabric wings. They
just make a hole and they go out the
other end and they don't explode. The
really difficult thing about torpedo
bombing and again I can't emphasize
enough doesn't matter whether you're in
the Swordfish or in any other torpedo
bomber. You have to do what is
completely alien to a pilot attacking
anything is fly in a straight line.
That's how you deliver torpedoes. So
your path is incredibly predictable to
an anti-aircraft gunner. So it's it's a
really really tough challenge.
The first attack which was delivered by
Swordfish torpedo bombers from
Victorious attacked in fading light in
rather poor condition. So they they were
not off to a terribly good start. They
only secured one hit and that struck the
Bismar roughly amid ships towards the
center. This was very unlucky for the
British because that was the center of
Bismar's armor belt and also where her
torpedo protection was most effective.
Like any other battleship, Bismar would
have had her standard hull plating. She
would have then had a layer of armor
bolted onto that. And for most of the
length of of the ship, there would have
been an additional layer of hole plating
with empty void spaces. In the event of
a torpedo strike, the blast would be
absorbed by the outer plating, and any
flooding would simply fill the void
space without damaging the hull beyond
it. That was the theory. It took an
awful lot of design work to get it
right, but Bismar's designers had done
their job very well there.
The attack was hardly the decisive blow
that the navy needed. Nevertheless, the
British shadow force was still glued to
Bismar following that oil slick trail.
For Bismar, though, that trail was only
one of her problems. Calculations by the
crew based on her remaining fuel supply
estimated that the most economical speed
for her to make it to a safe port was
now only 20 knots. It looked like the
tables were starting to turn a little
more against the German ship.
Lutens knew that he no longer had the
speed to make a clean break from his
pursuers, but he did have one key
advantage, and that was the British
didn't actually know where he was
heading. If Luchins couldn't outrun
them, he'd have to outsmart them.
Bismar was steaming across the Atlantic.
the tiniest needle in the most massive
hay stack and one that could go in any
direction at a moment's notice.
It was imperative for Norfolk, Suffukk,
and the Prince of Wales to remain in
contact with Bismar.
Without them relaying information back
to the rest of the fleet,
the hunt would become almost impossible.
The interesting thing about the Second
World War at this point is both sides
are fighting with and against technology
that hasn't been used in action before.
So the British are using radar, which is
a great advantage, but it's pretty crude
radar at this point in the war. It's
fairly short ranged. It's pretty
difficult to operate. Um, you know, the
the classic kind of rotating radar, they
don't have that. You kind of maneuver
the ship in order to to change the
direction of the radar. Um, equally the
Germans haven't fought against radar
before either, so they're kind of making
up tactics on the hoof to try and deal
with radar equipped opposition.
There was a message, as I understand it
from their boutique to say that we were
entering a very concentrated area of
Ubot and so we were given a course, a
zigzag course to pursue in case it was a
boat round.
I think this was the undoing of the
whole thing because as I understand it
from the radar people we had an echo on
one leg
on the other leg we didn't have an echo
at 3:00 a.m. On the 25th, Lutchins took
advantage of this break in the radar
coverage and ordered Bismar to go full
speed, 28 knots, and told his helmsman
to steer west before turning north. On
board Suffukk, the radar operator waited
for Bismar to reappear, but no signal
came in. Bismar had managed to turn
around behind her pursuers. It was the
dead of night. There was no radar
signal. The British had lost Bismar.
This whole maneuver by Legends was
probably one of the um most spectacular
pieces of timing he could have dreamt
up. Only by watching what the British
were doing and timing things to
perfection and knowing the limits and
speed of of his ship and the British
likely course meant that he had this
little window to achieve this. All he
did was loop out and sail round, curve
round to the north and went in behind uh
the British cruisers away from the the
pursuing home fleet and then he was
clear to head towards breast with
nothing between him and the French port.
>> Losing Bismar on radar, losing radar
contact is de a devastating blow for the
British. So previously, if you imagine
you've got you've got a speck in the
middle of the ocean, but you know where
that speck is, and the British are
vectoring everything they've got to get
the aircraft carriers within range,
bring the battleships in to engage.
Suddenly, they've lost that advantage.
They do not know where Bismar is. And
you're sitting there with a chart and
you know Bismar's speed and you're just
thinking there's a huge circle and the
ship could go in any direction within
that circle. So, this is a catastrophe
and it has to be dealt with as soon as
possible because the more time that
elapses since you last had contact, the
greater the variety of places she could
end up.
Fearing that alone they would be easy
prey should they run into Bismar in the
dead of night. The three British ships
decided to hunt for Bismar together.
With no better option other than to
guess, they altered their course west
and began steaming until daybreak.
When no contact was made, Rear Admiral
Wake Walker on board HMS Norfolk ordered
the three ships to break off and do a
daylight search for Bismar. They all
went in the wrong direction.
>> The time we lost contact was about 3:00
in the morning. I don't think we got to
know know about it until about 5 or 6
because then we were going in all
different directions
west of them and south Prince of Wales
went east I think and
to try and find
the tension on Bismar must have been
unbearable at this point because um
they've lost radar contact this is a
good thing but they know that it's only
a window they know that the most
powerful navy in the world is has almost
all its assets deployed to find them. Um
they know they're leaking oil. Um they
know the importance of finding and
sinking them. This will be to the
British. So they've got this window to
try and get home. Um and every effort
they made must have been dedicated to
doing that to pushing the ship through.
They knew they weren't out of trouble
yet. Even though they had been lost by
the British,
>> the British search became more frantic.
It was compounded by the rapidly
decreasing fuel levels on board all
searching ships which had been steaming
at full speed to try and intercept the
German.
On board Bismar, Lutens could never have
guessed that his maneuver would be so
successful. And so in a moment of
misjudgment, a long message was
transmitted from Bismar back to German
naval headquarters. A potential lifeline
had just been thrown.
That message was intercepted by the
British, which allowed them to estimate
Bismar's position. Those coordinates
were then immediately sent to Tovi's
flagship, King George V, where there was
a moment of spectacular incompetence.
The position was plotted wrongly on King
George V's charts. Tovi set a course to
intercept and spent the next seven hours
steaming in completely the wrong
direction.
As night began to fall, Bismar's
position had been unknown for almost 24
hours, and the Royal Navy were no closer
to locating her.
In the darkness of the night, the chance
of her being found was zero. Bismar
could steam on towards a safe harbor,
almost certainly unopposed.
She could be anywhere within thousands
of square miles of ocean.
As Churchill went to bed on the night of
the 25th, he announced, "These three
days have been the worst yet."
As Churchill and the Navy High Command
waited on the brink of despair,
information came in from Bletchley Park
that offered a glimmer of hope. It was a
decrypted order from the Lufafa telling
its units to redeploy in order to
protect Bismar as it neared the French
port of Breast. Now the Navy had an
inkling of where Bismar was heading and
they scrambled to put together a plan to
stop her.
As the hours ticked on, the chances of
finding and catching Bismar were
increasingly unlikely.
Searches had been constant. Longrange
flying boats scoured thousands of square
miles of empty ocean looking for Bismar.
But now with the information that Bismar
was heading for breast, they could
finally concentrate their search.
Then after over 30 hours of searching at
10:30 on the 26th of May, Enson Leonard
B. Smith, an American on a Catalina
flying boat out of Northern Ireland,
spotted a rainbow oil slick on the sea.
and then Bismar
Smith immediately called in the
position. The German was making a decent
speed and was just 800 miles from
Breast.
It was electrifying news. Bismar had
been found, but the Navy would have to
act fast. They calculated Bismar's speed
and bearing and realized that within
less than a day, Bismar would be safely
back under the protective air umbrella
of Lufafa aircraft from breast. That
meant that most of the Royal Navy ships
in the Atlantic had no chance of
catching her. But the Navy did have one
card left to play. Force H.
So, Force H is is an interesting beast
and it's a really classic example of of
how you have to improvise in wartime.
Um, so if you just trap back to to 1940,
British strategy in the Mediterranean is
based around operating with the French.
The French are going to cover the
Western Mediterranean. The British are
going to cover the East and that's job
done. France drops out of the war in the
summer of 1940 and the Western
Mediterranean is uncovered. So what
would have been a French responsibility,
the British have to pull together some
ships from elsewhere and create a force
based on Gibraltar that can operate in
the western Mediterranean and also out
into the Atlantic, which is what the
French would have done. Vice Admiral
Somerville's force H was centered around
his flagship, the small battle cruiser
Renown. She was accompanied by the
aircraft carrier Ark Royal and a
cruiser, a light cruiser, the Sheffield.
So they were now powering north through
the Bay of Bisque and on to try to
intercept Bismar.
>> Force H needed to get their aircraft
carrier Ark Royal into a position to
launch her torpedo bombers to repeat the
attack of a few days before. This time
the Navy was in even more desperate need
of success.
However, as they drew in to only 70 mi
from Bismar, the Atlantic swell started
to grow and the weather closed in. It
was now or never. The swordfish had to
be launched or Bismar would surely never
be caught.
The swordfish were fitted with new
magnetic torpedoes. Then in the early
afternoon, with the deck pitching
through 55 foot waves and the teeth of
violent gale, 14 Swordfish aircraft
lumbered into the sky. They were
carrying not only their bombs, but the
hopes and expectations of the entire
nation.
And we climbed up to about 8,000 9,000
ft. And although it was blowing hard and
there was a big sea running, the weather
then was the visibility was good and
there was a lot of broken cloud and we
could see the target as we are being led
in through gaps in the cloud and down we
went in our dive and turned in to the
attack. Now, I had my doubts as we went
down because I could see the ship and
she wasn't firing at us and I thought,
well, that's odd. You know, previous
attacks that I had down, the ship was
firing at us in the dive. And as I
leveled out on the water, I saw other
aircraft dropping their torpedoes. And I
looked at the ship and I said, "That is
a townass cruiser. I don't know which
one, but it is a townass cruiser." And
it had its battle white ensons up and so
I didn't drop my torpedo. My leader did.
He dropped his but I held on to mine.
The majority had just dropped their
torpedoes on HMS Sheffield, the cruiser
from Force H that had steamed up with
Ark Royal from Gibraltar. It was another
colossal error by the Royal Navy.
Well, now when we got back to the ship,
they told us that it was Sheffield, but
in the briefing, you see, they never
told us that Sheffield had been
detached. We didn't know she was there.
The signal to detach the Sheffield to
shadow the Bismar was not repeated to
Art Royal.
Fortunately for the Sheffield, the
torpedoes either missed or
malfunctioned, but it was another
horrible mistake. more precious hours
wasted in that race to catch Bismar.
>> So that the clock is ticking now and and
you know that the the odds are are
starting to stack against the British.
Um the the failed attack on on Sheffield
is a disaster really because it just
costs time. So what the what they have
to do now is is get those strike
aircraft back onto Art Royal, get them
down below decks, get new torpedoes on
them, get back up again, and redeploy
the strike force. That all takes a long
time to do. You can imagine how frenetic
it would have been down in Art Royals
hanger as each aircraft drops down
getting those those new weapons on on
very quickly. You've got tired air crew
who have already done one one mission.
But nevertheless, they take the
decision. They're going to try for one
last strike before it gets dark. And
really, if it gets dark and they haven't
done something significant to slow
Bismar down, that the chances of her
getting home safely are getting greater
and greater if she gets another night
steaming.
At 1910, the rearmed swordfish were
launched off a lurching ark royal.
The battleships that had the best chance
of battering Bismar, Rodney and King
George V, were still a distance away and
starting to run low on fuel.
Rodney could only keep up its pursuit
for another 12 hours. King George V
radioed Rodney.
Through filthy weather, the swordfish
bore down on their target. It was now or
never. In a side of things to come for
naval warfare, one of the most important
strikes in the history of the Royal Navy
was now being delivered by aircraft.
When the attack actually came, it was in
little penny packets of aircraft,
dropping down through the clouds,
finding this German battleship in front
of them, and then carrying out their
attacks.
We turned in and made our attack down to
90 ft. Dropped the fish, turned hard
down wind and jked all over the sky. And
of course the ship itself, you could see
all the guns firing at you with a tracer
in green, red, orange, white, all coming
towards you.
Suddenly there were great eruptions of
spray going up in the air and and we
realized that she was firing her main
armament at us in the hope that you know
they'd drop a shell kind of somewhere
near and we'd be swamped by the by the
spray.
The attack by the bombers from Ark Royal
succeeded much more than the previous
attacks had done. Um, again due to luck,
but this time luck had shifted in the
British direction and away from the
Germans. When the bombers first
approached, the conditions were very
similar to the ones that had stied
Victorious's planes. Um, the weather was
rough. Bismar was free to maneuver. So
even though she was a large target, she
was making it difficult for them. And
that very impressive anti-aircraft
battery of hers was putting up an awful
lot of flack. What is remarkable under
the conditions is that two torpedoes
struck their mark. One, like the
previous attack, struck the ship where
her anti- torpedo protection was
strongest and did no appreciable damage.
But the second one was far more far more
effective and far more dangerous for
Bismar. That torpedo hit struck right
after in the vicinity of her propeller
and rudders. Now, fortunately for the
Germans, the propellers were not damaged
by the blast. That could have been even
more fatal. But what did happen was that
the torpedo struck just as Bismar was
making an evasive turn to port. And it
meant that her rudders were now jammed
15° to port. If that damage could not be
made good, Bismar, who was so close to
escaping from the pursuing British, was
now stuck uh only able to steam in
circles.
Even in the immediate aftermath of the
attack, the identity of the man who
dropped the crucial torpedo was unclear.
Until recently, it was accepted that
Jock Moffett made the decisive strike.
But recent research has suggested that
in fact the man who disabled Bismar was
Kenneth Patterson.
And as we turned away, my observer, he
looked over the side of the aircraft,
the stern, and saw our torpedo actually
running. You could see the wake of it in
the in the sea. And I knew that I'd
aimed off for her speed. And as I was in
the better position to to the attack, I
I'm quite sure it was my torpedo.
>> It was a one ina- million shot. Bismar
was now helpless. Steering in a sweeping
circle. [sighs]
They tried to repair the ship, but it
was hopeless. Lutons knew the game was
up. the British fleet would be on his
position within hours. At 2140, he
radioed his headquarters with Bismar's
position
and a statement of defiance.
That night, the crew of Bismar were
allowed to raid the stock cupboards.
gorging themselves on ham, tinned
pineapple, and rum. An announcement was
made over the PA. The German people are
with you, and we will fight until our
gun barrels glow redot and the last
shell has left the barrels. For us
seaman, the question is now victory or
death.
The minute that torpedo disables the
steering gear, the heart must have been
ripped out of Bismar ship's company. Bis
the Germans cannot win at this point. So
where the odds were starting to go in
their favor a little bit, if they just
managed to evade that one last torpedo
strike, they may have had a really good
chance of getting home, getting under
that Luftwaffer fighter umbrella and
getting into breast. That chance is now
gone. They really can, to paraphrase
Raider at the beginning of the war,
their only option now is is to die
bravely. They're not going to win this
action. They're steaming in a circle.
They're leaving a telltale trail of oil.
They can't, if you imagine it, they're
not only an easy, predictable target,
but they also can't fire their own guns
properly because they're steaming in a
circle. And the entire Royal Navy is
looking for them. And they have to spend
this long night waiting for this to
happen. So, absolutely unbearable
tension on board.
>> But it wouldn't be a quiet night of rest
and preparation for the Germans. British
destroyers swarmed around Bismar,
harassing the Leviathan as the British
fleet closed in. By dawn on the 27th,
King George V and Rodney were finally in
range. Once again, the British had big
guns trained on Bismar.
She was now within range of Admiral Tovi
in King George V and the even more
powerful battleship Rodney. Away to the
north was the Ark Royal with her
aircraft standing by to launch another
strike. And then to the to the south and
the northeast were two British heavy
cruisers. Dorsucher to coming up from
the south and Norfolk who had been
shadowing her from the first was
approaching from from the northeast. So
Bismar was finally being hemmed in by
these British forces.
The British battleships that are closing
in to finish off Bismar in her final
hours are a rather odd mismatched pair.
On on the one hand you have King George
V who is a very modern battleship
completed roughly around the same time
slightly be earlier than Bismar. Um and
in many respects a comparable ship. She
has different guns, slightly smaller, 14
in, but she has 10 of them. Her armor
protection is every bit as comprehensive
as Bismar's. And in some respects, her
armor protection to vital areas is is
marginally better. Um, like Bismar, she
also has very comprehensive anti-
flooding um arrangements, although some
would argue not as comprehensive as
Bismar, but it's quibbling over small
change. The only area where she's
slightly behind Bismar is in speed. As
designed, she's one or two knots slower.
So, it's not unfair to say that King
George V and Bismar are very closely
matched in ideal circumstances.
Rodney is a rather curious beast.
Completed in 1927, she is a much older
ship, but she is also an extremely
powerful one. Uh Rodney and her sister
Nelson were the first ships in the Royal
Navy to mount 16in guns and she has nine
of these weapons. So her broadside is
much heavier than Bismar's. In terms of
armor protection, she's a very different
animal. She follows a very different
protection scheme uh whereby the most
vital areas have extremely thick armor
and the less vital areas have hardly
any. The only area where Rodney falls
behind Bismar is in speed. As designed,
she can only make 23 knots. So, had
Bismar been free to maneuver, she could
have simply run away from Rodney if she
didn't fancy her chances. Her exhausted
crew had been at action stations and
therefore without sleep for nearly 24
hours. They'd been constantly attacked.
They'd been harassed during the night by
destroyers. Um, they were tired. They
were demoralized. And now here were two
fresh British battleships who had yet to
see action uh with crews who were ready,
who were well trained, familiar with
their ships.
In ideal circumstances, either British
ship would have had a 50/50 chance of
defeating Bismar. I believe u in the
circumstances of the 27th of May 1941,
both British battleships made Bismar's
defeat a certainty.
At 0847, HMS Rodney opened up with her
massive 16-in guns,
followed shortly after by King George V.
Bismar had been hunted down. Now she
needed to be sunk.
At 0850, Bismar's guns roared in reply,
but buffed by heavy seas, unable to
steer properly, Bismar found it
impossible to fire accurately. This
allowed the smaller British ships like
jackals to close in and start firing
their 8-in guns. At 9:02,
disaster befell Bismar. One of Rodney's
massive 16-in shells smashed into the
ship. Survivors suggest it might even
have hit the bridge itself. Hundreds
were killed, including probably
Linderman and Lutchins. Bismar's command
and control had been shot away. It was
now only a matter of time.
We
closed the range and we came in from
27,000 y finally to about um 4,000 yards
um and were pumping stuff into her
pretty hard.
And she kept up a desolate fire for a
long time. Very very brave action. Um
because although we failed to sink her,
we certainly we we knocked her about and
she was um
on fire in many places. A lot of smoke
and you could see the shells crumping
against her side.
So what you've got now is is a really
brutal one-sided battle. And the British
don't have any choice. There can't
there's no room for sentimentality in
this. This ship needs to be sunk and
unless the Germans strike their colors
and surrender, which they're not going
to do. There's no option but just to
keep pummeling and pummeling at close
range.
These 14-in shells and 16in shells, plus
lighter shells were joining in even from
the cruisers. 18in shells were starting
to pound the Bismar into submission.
Despite colossal damage to the ship and
her chain of command, Bismar fought on.
A wounded animal in its death throws.
0927. Bismar fired her final salvo
before more British shells smashed into
the ship.
By 0931, all four main turrets were out
of action. The fight was all but over.
Tovi had ordered that there was to be no
let up until the Germans struck their
ensom. Basically took down their battle
flag as a sign of surrender. The problem
was that eyewitnesses remember that by
this stage the the deck of Bismar was a
smoking ruined hellscape. There were no
flag heliards to be raised and lowered
by that point. Anyway, the battering
continued nonstop.
Aboard Rodney, the chaplain took the
extraordinary step of confronting the
captain directly to plead with him to
stop the attack. He was ordered politely
to mind his own business. And the shells
kept flying.
It was rather a bloody business.
One had to go on
to sink the ship, but there were people
occasionally. I saw a few of them
running after, jumping over the side
while we were still engaging her.
So, you just imagine this ship being
relentlessly hit by 16in and 14in
armorpiercing shells and then by torpedo
strike. She's on fire. She's listing.
The conditions on board were absolutely
frightful. We we know that from from
eyewitnesses who survived the sinking.
Now, the evidence seems to be that that
the crew ultimately scuttled their own
ship. Um, there is a tradition of this
in the German Navy that really probably
begins with the the high seas fleet at
the end of the First World War. It's
seen as a a more honorable way of, you
know, ending the battle if you've you've
scuttled your own ship rather than let
the enemy do it. Um, it's academic and I
can't emphasize this enough. Bismar is
going down. Bismar will be sunk. This
was a fight to the death and it was not
just a matter of revenge for the Hood,
although that was probably an element of
it. What essentially this was was about
ending that threat to Britain's Atlantic
sealings.
At 10:20, the demolition charges were
blown at around the same time as HMS
Dorsuch was told to close in and sink
Bismar with her torpedoes.
20 minutes later at 10:40, the firing
finally stopped and Bismar, the pride of
Adolf Hitler's Navy, sank beneath the
waves of the Atlantic.
Bismar had a crew of 2,200 men.
Only 114
survived the awful ordeal.
Shortly after Bismar sank, the message
was relayed back to the Admiral T.
Admiral Toby later said the Bismar had
put up a most gallant fight against
impossible odds worthy of the old days
of the Imperial German Navy and she went
down with her colors flying.
Bismar's final hours are a tribute to
the bravery of her crew and the quality
of her design and her construction. The
British had ranged everything from
battleships all the way down to
destroyers in the final action and there
were even bombers on standby to finish
the job if necessary. Uh Bismar took a
very impressive amount of killing. But
it is worth noting that although she
took hours to defeat and sink, the
unsinkability which was prized so much
in her design could not guarantee the
maintenance of her fighting power. And
it's noteworthy that very quickly into
her final engagement, Bismar's fighting
power is progressively broken so rapidly
that in contrast to her victory on the
24th of May, this mighty warship did not
manage to land one single significant
hit on any of her tormentors before the
end came.
>> People say that that the Royal Navy were
lucky to get away with the Bismar
action. I really don't think that's fair
at all. I think I think there is luck in
any action. They say no plan survives
contact with the enemy. The minute that
the shells start to fly um and things
start to break down and things start to
to malfunction, you need luck. The
Germans get some luck. You can argue
that they're lucky to destroy Hood. Um
they're kind of lucky to break radar
contact. The British get that luck with
the torpedo strike in the end. You
cannot take luck out of the equation in
any battle.
Bismar's first and only operation had
lasted just 9 days, but it was nine days
of the highest drama for both sides
and an action that would cast a long
shadow.
The whole Bismar campaign was a bit of a
watershed both for the criggs marine and
the Royal Navy. for the Germans
essentially stopped any more idea of
sending large capital ships out into the
Atlantic from that point on that could
only be done with hubot.
>> The other instruction that that comes
from the top in Germany is that um
German warships, surface warships um
when they're mostly operating in the
Arctic are not allowed to engage a
British force that has an aircraft
carrier with it. And there is a constant
question about you know anytime they
contemplate sending out turpets or
charhorse to raid the arctic convoy
routes the first question is where are
the aircraft carriers there is aircraft
carrier fright within the German navy
from this point
>> for the British it meant that they no
longer had to keep a so many units
defending its its convoy routes. some of
those vitely needed capital ships and
aircraft carriers could be sent where
they can make a big difference in the
Mediterranean or even round to the Far
East.
>> The British are very very aware of how
close the Germans came to pulling this
off. If it really if it wasn't for the
the Catalina that finds her in the
middle of the Atlantic and then the
swordfish that puts a torpedo into her
steering gear, Bismar could have got
home. And so what what the British
learning from this whole business is
that actually they deployed almost the
entire Royal Navy, countless capital
ships, cruisers, destroyers, two
aircraft carriers, and this one German
raiders still nearly made it home after
sinking a British capital ship. So that
then imposes real problems for the
British when Turpets, Bismar's identical
sister, appears. Now Turpitz does almost
nothing in the Second World War. She she
does very very little. She sits in
Norway, the lonely queen of the north.
But the Royal Navy remain obsessed with
her and maintain an incredibly strong
home fleet at Scappaflow in the Ornney
basically because of Turpets because
they have the fear that if Turpets
breaks out, they will have to do this
all over again and they might not get as
lucky the next time.
The hunting and sinking of Bismar was
also a key stage in the shifting nature
of naval warfare.
The final battle was almost something
straight out of Jutland and that was one
of the last flings of the battleship.
The first half of the Second World War
is characterized by a realization that
battleships are not the capital ship
anymore and they are vulnerable and they
are vulnerable to carrierbased aviation.
Um we it's a lesson that that was was
learned at Toronto. It was then learned
in the Bismar action. It's learned again
at Pearl Harbor and with the loss of the
Prince of Wales and repulse to Japanese
aircraft. Battleships have had their
day. What they are now is is big
floating gun platforms that have to be
surrounded and protected by other ships
and by airplanes.
But Bismar had been sunk. [music]
Britain had successfully seen off the
greatest naval challenge it had faced
thus far in the Second World War.
Britain's supply lines across the
Atlantic remained intact. The price had
been high. Hood lost and Bismar [music]
had showed up shortcomings in British
naval doctrine and equipment. But even
though it was closer than she might have
liked, Britannia [music] still ruled the
waves.
>> [music]